

RESEARCHER IN PRIVACY, SECURITY AND COMPUTATIONAL TRUST

Diasta Ekoda no Mori 503, 2-20-3 Toyotama-kita, Nerima-ku, Tokyo 176-0012, Japan

□ (+81) 80-3315-8649 | ☑ a.basu@xtremebytes.com | ♠ http://www.anirbanbasu.com | 匝 anirbanbasu

"There is only one corner of the universe you can be certain of improving, and that's your own self." – Aldous Huxley

Summary.

With more than a decade of research and innovation experience within both academia and industry, I have co-authored 70+ research papers and submitted about 20 co-authored Japanese patent applications. My publications have been cited more than 1,000 times setting my overall h-index to 15 (source: Google Scholar). The areas of research that interest me include, but are not limited to: computational trust systems, privacy and risk, privacy preserving data mining, artificial intelligence and ethics, cybersecurity, distributed consensus, and the Internet of Things. I like building things to solve real-world problems. Outside research and problem solving, I am keen on photography, videography and the associated travels.

Professional experience

Hitachi, Ltd.Yokohama, Japan

SEARCHER Oct. 2018 – present

• **Summary:** Researcher in computational trust systems at the Security Research Department (Center for Technology Innovation – Systems Engineering) within the Hitachi Research & Development group, which is a part of Hitachi, Ltd.

Freelancer Tokyo, Japan

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER, TECHNOLOGY AND RESEARCH CONSULTANT

Aug. 2014 - present

• Summary: Developing software, providing technology and research consulting services to organisations mainly in Japan and Europe.

KDDI Research, Inc. Fujimino, Japan

SENIOR RESEARCHER

May. 2013 – Apr. 2018

• Highlights: Within the Information Security Laboratory, worked on (a) a multi-institutional EUR 3M EU-Japan Horizon 2020 funded project to realise a secure data storage and privacy-preserving analytics engine over heterogeneous multi-cloud environments spanning across national borders; and (b) a Toyota ITC and KDDI Research jointly funded collaborative project with ISTI-CNR and the University of Pisa on privacy risks in trajectory data.

Tokai University Tokyo, Japan

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Oct. 2010 - Mar. 2013

• Highlights: Developed a privacy-preserving collaborative filtering scheme over encrypted domain and demonstrated the feasibility in real-world public cloud environments – the Google App Engine and the Amazon Elastic Beanstalk – as part of a multi-institutional JPY 500M+ Japanese government funded project on privacy-preserving data mining on the cloud.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

ASSOCIATE TUTOR (OCT. 2004 – JAN. 2010) AND RESEARCH FELLOW (OCT. 2008 – SEP. 2009)

Oct. 2004 – Jan. 2010

• Highlights: Re-developed a course module on electronic commerce technologies for the Masters degree programme funded by American Express. Worked in two (GBP 1M and GBP 1.4M) EPSRC funded research projects related to computational trust.

Freelancer Brighton, UK

TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT (JUL. 2005 – SEP. 2008; JUN. 2010 – SEP. 2010)

Jul. 2005 - Sep. 2010

• Highlights: Technology consultant to the University of Sussex library. Developed Java Web Services hooks for Class Calendar Ltd. Codeveloped computational skills training videos for Claro Training Ltd.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

STEP SUMMER INTERN (JUL. 2003 – Aug. 2003) and then Research Assistant

Jul. 2003 – Sep. 2004

- Highlights: Developed a lightweight augmented reality based visualisation technology based on backend XML-based storage as part of a €2.8M EU Framework Programme V funded project on digital cultural heritage.
- Award: Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP, UK) Local Finalist.

Professional affiliations

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW

Jan. 2010 – present

· Collaborative research with the Foundations of Software Systems (FoSS) group in the Department of Informatics.

IFIP Trust Management (IFIPTM)

Tokyo, Japan

PUBLICITY CHAIR (JUN. 2010 – JUN. 2015) AND SECRETARY (JUN. 2015 – PRESENT)

Jun. 2010 – present

• Contributing to the IFIP Working Group 11.11 – Trust Management (IFIPTM), the premier venue on computational trust management research.

• Contributing to the HTP Working Group H.H. – Hust Management (HTP 1M), the premier venue on computational trust management tesearch

Rutgers University
VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW

Newark, NJ, USA

Oct. 2014 - Sep. 2017

• Collaborative research with Prof. Jaideep Vaidya at the Rutgers Business School.

Education

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (D.PHIL.) IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE

Oct. 2004 - Feb. 2010

- Supervisors: Prof. Ian Wakeman and Dr. Dan Chalmers.
- Examiners: Dr. Des Watson (University of Sussex) and Prof. David Parish (Loughborough University)
- **Doctoral thesis:** 'A Reputation Framework for Behavioural History' proposed a high-level, generalised, policy-independent and context-aware framework to build and share reputations of network clients based on their behavioural history in order to inform future interactions. PDF: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-dphil2010.pdf.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING (B.Eng.) IN COMPUTER SYSTEMS ENGINEERING

Oct. 2001 - Jun. 2004

- Grade: First Class Honours.
- Awards: (1) IEE Sussex Branch local prize for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.); and (2) the Eurotherm company prize for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project.
- Final year project: 'ARCOLite a visualisation system for viewing museum artefacts' presented a lightweight XML-based repository and a desktop visualisation in both virtual and augmented reality. PDF: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-beng2004.pdf.

Accolades

INVITED TALKS

2018	World Wide Web Foundation , Privacy – connecting the dots	London, UK
2017	IFIP TM – Doctoral Symposium, Homomorphic Encryption – an answer to privacy?	Göteborg, Sweden
2015	Kyushu University – Next Generation Cryptography , Homomorphic Encryption – are we there yet?	Fukuoka, Japan
2012	CSA – SecureCloud , Practical privacy using homomorphic encryption – a myth or reality	Frankfurt, Germany

AWARDS

2004	IEE Sussex Branch local prize , for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.)	Brighton, UK
2004	Eurotherm company prize, for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project	Brighton, UK
2003	Local Finalist, Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP)	Brighton, UK

SCHOLARSHIPS

2004	Graduate Teaching Assistantship (2004–2007), Department of Informatics (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK
2001	Dean's Bursary (2001–2004), Department of Engineering and Design (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK

Publications

A full list of publications is available at: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/#research.

Research papers

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] M. S. Rahman, A. Basu, T. Nakamura, H. Takasaki, and S. Kiyomoto, "PPM: Privacy Policy Manager for Home Energy Management," Journal of Wireless Mobile Networks, Ubiquitous Computing and Dependable Applications (JoWUA), vol. 9, no. 2, pp. 42–56, 2018.
- [2] **A. Basu**, M. S. Rahman, R. Xu, K. Fukushima, and S. Kiyomoto, "VIGraph A Framework for Verifiable Information," in *Proceedings of the IFIP WG 11.11 International Conference on Trust Management (IFIPTM)*, Göteborg, Sweden, 2017, pp. 12–20.
- [3] **A. Basu**, A. Monreale, R. Trasarti, J. C. Corena, F. Giannotti, D. Pedreschi, S. Kiyomoto, Y. Miyake, and T. Yanagihara, "A risk model for privacy in trajectory data," *Journal of Trust Management*, vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 1–23, 2015.
- [4] J. Vaidya, I. Yakut, and **A. Basu**, "Efficient Integrity Verification for Outsourced Collaborative Filtering," in *Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM)*, Shenzhen, China, 2014.
- [5] **A. Basu**, J. Vaidya, H. Kikuchi, and T. Dimitrakos, "Privacy-preserving collaborative filtering on the cloud practical implementation experiences," in *Proceedings of the IEEE Cloud*, Santa Clara, CA, USA, 2013.
- [6] **A. Basu**, S. Fleming, J. Stanier, S. Naicken, I. Wakeman, and V. K. Gurbani, "The state of peer-to-peer network simulators," *ACM Computing Surveys*, vol. 45, no. 4, pp. 46:1–46:25, 08 2013.

Patents (including pending) and public information

JAPAN PATENT OFFICE APPLICATION NUMBERS

2013-141965, 2013-171600, 2013-202289, 2013-232080, 2013-272722, 2014-020802, 2014-054142, 2014-094155, 2014-149798, 2014-128201, 2014-177250, 2015-158205, 2015-046346, 2015-180642, 2016-066512, 2017-018877, 2017-018878, 2017-029170, 2017-029171, 2017-029172, 2017-099572, 2017-096380, 2017-198726, 2018-001096.

Skills___

OS: MacOS, Windows, Linux, UNIX; Documents: MS Office, Google Docs and Etc.; Software development: Java, C#, Objective-C, Computing skills

C++, Visual C++, C, Visual Basic, XML, Javascript, UML, Subversion, Git, JUnit, Ant, Mayen, MySQL, JBoss, Tomcat, Google App

Engine, Amazon Elastic Beanstalk. (Non-exhaustive list.)

Languages English (fluent), Bengali (native), Japanese (elementary), Hindi (elementary)

UPDATED: JANUARY 6, 2019 ANIRBAN BASU | CURRICULUM VITÆ 2 OF 2